Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf ק"ך. Kuf-Chaf. We are
three דפים dapim to go, the שלושת ימי הגבלה. Shloshet Yemei Hagbala.
We pick up at the let's read the very four lines from
the bottom on קי"ט עמוד ב'. Kuf-yud-tet amud-bet. Let's do a little
review from what we did yesterday. So in the משנה, Mishna, the
case is a woman comes, two women who are married to two
brothers. Each one reports on their husband's death. And each one is
believed that their husband has died in order to allow them to
remarry. The only thing is, is that a woman is only believed
or somebody's only believed about the death of a husband in order
that the wife can remarry or for the woman herself to remarry.
She is not believed on it vis-a-vis allowing her sister-in-law to assume
that her brother-in-law has died, right? So, you know, let's say, let's
take even a simpler case. Somebody comes and reports, a woman has
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. Her brother-in-law is somewhere in a
far-away country and somebody comes and says that the brother-in-law died. So
you're not- you know, that is, you know, you know, that's- that's
a different story. You're not believed to say for that type of
a testimony to get somebody out of the מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
yibum. Particularly here also because it's the whole issue of sister-in-law not
being believed by sister-in-law. But the thing that complicates it is, is
that the thing that complicates it is that what do you call
it? Is that each woman is believed about, about the
death in terms of, in terms of her own ability to remarry.
So here you have two brothers,
right?
Here you have ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, okay? And here their
two wives, okay? And these are brothers, okay? So this woman, so
here. So this woman says, here we'll be רחל Rachel and שרה,
Sarah, we'll map it, ר' Resh and ש'. Shin. Okay. So anyway,
רחל Rachel says her husband is dead. So she's believed. And she
can in theory remarry if there was nobody else. שרה Sarah says
her husband is dead. She'd be believed to remarry. The only thing
is that רחל Rachel knows that ראובן's Reuven got a brother and
שרה Sarah knows that שמעון's Shimon got a brother, right? And therefore
they can't remarry because there's a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum or
חליצה. chalitza. Now we have testimony from רחל's Rachel perspective that שמעון
Shimon is dead, but that testimony doesn't work for her. It's her
sist- you know, it's a sister-in-law's testimony which doesn't work, it's a
testimony about יבום yibum not about marriage and so on. So basically
they're stuck. They know their husbands are dead but they can't accept
each other's testimony about the brother-in-law. That's the case in the משנה.
Mishna. The משנה Mishna basically says that they are stuck. Comes along
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if they
went ahead and did יבום yibum with the other- with other brothers,
okay?
Right here's the other brothers, לוי Levi and יהודה. Yehuda.
So even if there might be, this one of these brothers might
be alive, they can't accept the testimony, but these are living brothers,
so they go ahead and they do יבום yibum and then those
brothers dies. Then רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer says, then they can go
ahead and remarry and they don't have to worry that one of
these guys is alive. So why not? What difference does it make?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara understands. Now the simple explanation of
רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer is what משנה Mishna says at the end,
which it says if you read the last line of the משנה,
Mishna, רבי אליעזר אומר הואיל והותרו ליבמין הותרו לכל אדם. Rabbi Eliezer
omer, ho’il vehutru leyavmim hutru lechol adam.
Once we've believed that רחל's Rachel testimony that ראובן Reuven was dead
to allow her to do יבום yibum with לוי, Levi, and שרה's
Sarah testimony that שמעון Shimon was dead to allow her to do
יבום yibum with יהודה, Yehuda, meaning it's not just we've believed their
testimony in abstract. We've actually acted on their testimony about their own
husbands to let them remarry. Then it's like he- but he's basically
saying is, then the fact that ראובן Reuven has died has been
established as the fact, right? Because we let רחל Rachel go ahead
and do יבום. yibum. And the fact that שמעון Shimon is dead
has been established as at least legal, right? As a legal fact.
Because we allow שרה Sarah to do יבום yibum with יהודה. Yehuda.
So once we've ex- once they've acted on their testimony and done
יבום, yibum, now if these guys die, they can assume the other
guy is dead here and that they can go ahead and remarry.
Because now שרה's Sarah entitled to assume that ראובן Reuven is dead
because רחל Rachel has already acted on that on that, you know,
on that fact that ראובן Reuven is dead and vice versa. So
that's what רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer says, that after these guys, if
they did יבום yibum here and these guys dies, now now they're
free to remarry because now these have- it's actually been acted upon,
the testimony that their husbands are dead.
Okay, so now- so now let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. So אמר בעי רבא. Amar ba’ei Rava. רבא Rava asked, four
lines from the bottom,
מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר משום דקסבר צרה מעידה לחברתה.
Mai ta’ama deRabbi Eliezer?
Mishum dekasavar tzara me’ida lachavirtah. Maybe basically he holds in general, you
know, competing wives can testify for one another, like a sister-in-law or
so on. Now of course that's crazy, not crazy, whatever, but we've
had a whole discussion about how these women in competition, you know,
mother-in-law, daughter-in-law, sister-in-law, whatever can't testify. Why all of a sudden would
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer say they could? And it's also not the
language of the משנה. Mishna. The language of the משנה Mishna is
הותרו ליבמין. hutru leyevamin. So תוספות Tosafot explicitly and רש"י Rashi implicitly
says no, no, no, what he means is when they are fundamentally
testifying for themselves. In this case, רחל Rachel is fundamentally saying her
husband has died to allow her to remarry, right? That's the basic
testimony is about herself and her husband. Maybe he's saying once that
was the basic purpose of the testimony, we'll accept it also for
her sister-in-law. And once שרה Sarah is basically testifying for herself that
שמעון Shimon died, we'll accept it also for her sister-in-law and it'll
work for ראובן, Reuven, right? Which is a simple point that he's
saying. If you're accepting their testimony, you might as well accept it
completely. So even though now we're applying it to a woman who
normally wouldn't be believed for another woman, but that's because fundamentally we're
already believing it for the woman herself and then we'll apply it.
Okay, so is that what he holds? Thank you. Is he holds
that that basically it's there when they're testifying for themselves, it will
be believed even for their sister-in-law? או דילמא, o dilma, or is
it possible, משום דהיא לא מקלקלה נפשה, mishum de'hi lo mekalkela nafsha,
that it's not just that רחל Rachel came to testify for herself,
it's that she testified for herself and she acted on it. She
married, she did יבום yibbum with לוי. Levi. When you have those
two factors, she testified for herself and she acted on it, then
you can accept her testimony for שמעון, Shimon, right? And שרה Sarah
also, she testified for herself and she acted on it, she did
יבום. yibbum. Then if she's willing not only to make that claim
for herself but to act on it, then you believe that it's
true and you can apply it also to the other wife. So
basically רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is saying it's clear that רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer saying since you've accepted their testimony, the other wife can
also act on it, can also accept it. And רבא'ס Rava's question
is, is it just because they said the testimony for themselves or
is it also because they acted on it? One minute and let's
see the גמרא Gemara spells out. למאי נפקא מינה, lemai nafka mina,
what would be the difference? Easy difference, לאינסובה לצרה מקמי דידה, le'insuvei
letsara mikamei didah, let's say to let the co-wife get married before
her. Okay, so basically a woman comes and says that,
let's take a case where it is much simpler case, right? Much
simpler case is you have two co-wives,
now co-wives are a simple case. Okay, and the husband went to
מדינת הים, medinat hayam, okay? And שרה Sarah says he died. Okay,
so now based on what we're saying, well, if שרה Sarah said
she died, so that's to allow שרה Sarah herself to remarry, right?
So she's testifying for herself. Can now the other wife go ahead
and marry? רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says if they're testifying for yourself
and you're believed, now the other wife can also accept it. So
the question is when can רחל Rachel act on it? Can רחל
Rachel act on it immediately or can רחל Rachel act on it
only after שרה Sarah has gone and gotten married? Okay? Is רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer saying a testimony for oneself, which is believed, works
for the other woman, automatically works for the other woman, or works
for the other woman only when you've shown you yourself really, really
believe in it and you yourself act on it? Okay? So only
after יבום, yibbum, so this case where there's no יבום, yibbum, right,
maybe it'll only, maybe רחל Rachel can only accept that her husband
is dead after שרה Sarah has actually married someone. לאינסובה לצרה מקמי
דידה, le'insuvei letsara mikamei didah, for the co-wife to
marry before she does. אי אמרת צרה מעידה לחברתה, ei amart tsara
me'ida lechaverta,
if a wife can testify for a competing wife or, you know,
a competing woman, once she's already testifying for herself, it works for
one of the other women. אף אגב דלא אינסבא, af agav dela
insava, even if she herself did not get married, מנסבינן לה לצרה,
mansavinan lah letsara, we let the competing woman go ahead and get
married once a woman is testifying for herself, maybe רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer is saying we now can apply it to other women. That's
just the very testimony itself. אבל אי אמרת משום דהיא לא מקלקלה
נפשה, aval ei amart mishum de'hi lo mekalkela nafsha, no, it's only
because she acted on her own testimony and that makes it clear
that it was true, and she would not go and ruin herself,
then אינסבא, insava, if she got married, מנסבינן לה לצרה, mansavinan lah
letsara, we could let the co-wife get married. אבל אי לא אינסבא,
aval ei lo insava, if she didn't get married, לא מנסבינן לה,
lo mansavinan lah, we don't let the co-wife get married. מאי, mai,
what's the הלכה? halakha? So רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is clearly saying
once you accept the testimony, you can apply it to the other
woman, but the question is only when it's backed by this woman's
action or even before it's backed by this woman's action. So you
had a question.
Yeah, maybe before I came in you dealt with this, like for
119 pages we've had women waiting for the pronouncements of בית דין
Beis Din to clarify what they could do. Right. All of a
sudden the language of the case is the woman goes ahead and
acts on her own testimony without waiting for...
No, no, no, no, she, רחל Rachel testifies that ראובן Reuven is
dead or she testifies whatever and בית דין Beis Din says... Fine,
you're believed, go ahead get married. But what, but before שרה Sarah
actually acts on it, so it's with בית דין Beis Din acknowledging
it, but before שרה Sarah actually acts on it, can רחל Rachel
also act on it? That's within רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. בית דין's
Beis Din in the equation. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Is there an exception to the witness rule then, where even though
בית דין Beis Din said you're good, we're still like well,
right, because the whole idea that we believe a woman, or not
a woman, we believe an עד אחד, Ed Echad, we believe all
these things is only a special exception that we've made to witness
rules. And in order to allow a woman to get remarried. And
one of the exclusions to the exceptions, right, one of the limits
is these cases of competing women, right? So, but here the point
is, okay, but רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and until now we've assumed,
like the משנה Mishna assumes, you can split the testimony. For yourself
you're believed, not for this competing wife, right? But רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is saying no, once you're believed for yourself, you are believed
for this competing wife. And רבא's Rava question is, is it only
after you've acted on it, right, or even before? So let's take
a look. תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, הואיל והותרו ליבמים, ho'il vehuttru leyevamim, since we've allowed
them to marry the brother-in-laws, הותרו לכל אדם, huttru lechol adam, they've
been
their permissible to anybody. That's this case, right? So they go ahead
and they marry the brother-in-laws, brother-in-laws die, and now they can assume
that these guys are dead and go ahead and marry anyone they
want. Okay, but he says once they've been permitted. He didn't say
once they marry the brother-in-laws, he said once they've been permitted to
the brother-in-laws. הואיל והותרו ליבמים הותרו לכל אדם. Ho'il vehuttru leyevamim huttru
lechol adam. אי אמרת בשלמא דהיא לא מקלקלה נפשה עד דאינסבי מר
מיכא דאיכא דיוקא, Im amart bishlama dehi lo mekalkela nafsha ad de'insvei
mar micha de'ika diyuka, excuse me. If we say that the that
it's only once she acts on it and then she won't because
she won't go ahead and ruin herself, so she acted on it
we can believe it for the other wife. היינו דכי אינסב מנצבינא
לה, Hainu dechi insav manzveina leh,
that's why it says once they married the brother-in-laws, now they're permissible
to somebody else, only because they actually went ahead and did יבום.
yibum. אלא אי אמרת משום דצרה מעידה לחברתה, Ella im amart mishum
detzara mei'ida lachaverta,
if in principle they don't even have to act on it, it's
just that once they're testifying for themselves it works for someone else,
it works for the other you know for the competing woman, אף
על גב דלא אינסב נמי, af al gav delo insav nami, then
even before they've married the brother-in-laws it should have just said like
הואיל והותרו הותרו ho'il vehuttru huttru or something like that. אלא שמע
מינה טעמא דרבי אליעזר משום דאינסב היא ולא מקלקלה נפשה. Ella shema
mina ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer mishum de'insav hi velo mekalkela nafsha.
So you see that it sounds like רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer reason
is only once she got married, then can it be believed. הואיל
והותרו ליבמים, Ho'il vehuttru leyevamim, only after they went ahead and married
the brother-in-laws is it believed for the other wife. So that's what
it sounds like. So the גמרא Gemara says not necessarily. רבי אליעזר
לדבריהם קאמר. Rabbi Eliezer lidvreihem ka'amar. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying
back to the רבנן Rabbis according to their position. ולדידי, Ledidi, as
far as I'm concerned, צרה מעידה לחברתה, tzara mei'ida lachaverta, as automatically
the testimony is believed for the other woman once it's fundamentally testimony
for herself. ואף על גב דלא אינסב מנצבינא לה, Ve'af al gav
delo insav manzveina lah, and even if she didn't get married we
could marry off the co-wife. אלא לדידכו, Ella ledidchu, but
for for you, אודו לי מיחת הכא דאינסב מנצבינא לה, odu li
mi'at hachan de'insav manzveina lah, you should at least concede that after
they've married the brother-in-laws and now we've actually acted on it and
not only have we acted on it and like acknowledged it as
fact, but like how could we now suspect the woman of lying
if she's willing to go ahead and marry the brother-in-law and willing
to you know do this thing which would be a terrible transgression
for her, of course she must be telling the truth. So in
that case where she's acted on her own testimony, of course you
should concede that we should be able to believe it for the
co-wife. משום דהיא לא מקלקלה נפשה, Mishum dehi lo mekalkela nafsha,
she wouldn't go ahead and ruin her own life just in order
to mess up her this competing wife. So obviously if she's acted
on it we should believe it. ורבנן, VeRabbanan, and the רבנן Rabbis
would say back like we've seen before, no, תמות נפשי עם פלשתים
היא דקעבדא, tamus nafshi im pelishtim hi deka'avda,
she's willing to die with the Philistines. Okay, so she's willing to
take down the stadium on top of herself, you know, and ruin
her own life if in the process she'll manage to ruin the
life of her co-wife. Okay, but the point is yes, the גמרא
Gemara describes a scenario where they've went ahead and married the brother-in-laws
and that's the scenario that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says now we
can accept the testimony about these guys. But the גמרא Gemara is
saying that might just be he's arguing for the רבנן Rabbis that
that's at least a case they should concede in. But maybe he
himself would be prepared to believe their testimony even before her you
know they've acted on it. Once you're testifying for yourself, maybe you're
even believed for the for the competing wife, at least according to
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, yeah.
What would be the קלקול kilkul so to the צרה? tzara?
That she would go ahead and marry a man she wouldn't be
allowed to and then the husband would come back and it would
you know and would have all of the negative consequences, right? You
say
she says her husband is dead. So שרה Sarah thinks she has
no מצווה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, so she goes ahead and marries
some other guy without right and then he comes up and oh
you're אסורה, assura, you had to do חליצה chalitza dada dada, right?
Now, of course, the fact that you maybe did have to do
חליצה chalitza is not as consequential as your husband is still alive
and you're still married to your first husband. So תוספות Tosafos discusses
that like maybe you know it's a different type of a consequence
of of implications. All right. ורבנן VeRabbanan okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, so תא שמע, ta shma, we still don't
know the answer, let's hear. האישה שהלכה היא ובעלה למדינת הים, Ha'isha
she'halcha hi uba'ala lemdinat hayam, a woman and her husband went to
to Hawaii. ובאה ואמרה מת בעלי uva'ah ve'amra mes ba'ali and she
comes back and she says my husband has died. תנשא ותטול כתובתה
tinasei vetitol kesuvata she can get married and collect her כתובה kesuva
וצרתה אסורה vetzarata asura
and her co-wife is forbidden. That's a classic example that she's believed
for herself, not believed for the co-wife. And this is even after
she's acted on it. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the
co-wife should be permissible. So let's take a look. רבי אליעזר אומר
הואיל והותרה היא הותרה נמי צרתה. Rabbi Eliezer omer ho'il vehutra hee
hutra nami tzarata.
So you see he says that once she's permitted, the co-wife is
permitted. And it sounds like he's saying once she's permitted. It didn't
say once she got married. It didn't say she got married. It
said תנשא, tinasei, she's allowed to get married. In the משנה, Mishna,
the משנה Mishna described the cases where they married the brother-in-laws. So
the משנה Mishna makes it sound like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only
needs them to first act on it. That's the case in the
משנה. Mishna. They acted on it, they married the brother-in-laws. This ברייתא
Baraisa doesn't say she got they married. It says she's allowed to
get married. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says well if she's allowed,
the co-wife is allowed.
Okay.
So הואיל והותרה היא הותרה נמי צרתה, ho'il vehutra hee hutra nami
tzarata, so it sounds like just the it's automatically even before it's
acted on.
The same language as his earlier ברייתות Baraisos if she comes and
says let me collect my
כתובה kesuva we don't let her? Exactly. Exactly. The גמרא Gemara says:
אימא הואיל והותרה
וניסת.
eima ho'il vehutra
venisais. Alright, so read that into רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer statement. Not
once she's allowed, the co-wife is allowed. Once she's allowed and she
acts on it, then the co-wife is allowed. Alright, so by changing
the text. But the simple sense is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
doesn't need her to act on it yet. ולחוש שמא בגיטה אתאי,
veleichush shema begita asai,
the גמרא Gemara says one minute. If רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only
will accept it for the co-wife if the woman actually acts on
it, right? So what's the argument? We can't believe you for the
co-wife until you've shown that you're willing to, you know, risk yourself.
You yourself trust on the testimony and act on it. So the
גמרא Gemara says if that's our concern, then even when she acts
on it, it's not definite proof. Why not? I mean, isn't she
risking her own status? Well, maybe she has a גט. get. Maybe
her husband went to Hawaii, sent her a גט get in the
mail. Nobody else knows about it. So she's divorced and now she's
like great, now I'm divorced, I'll say he died and I'll marry
and I'll be okay because I'm divorced. She'll go ahead and she'll
marry and then she'll be totally ruined because he'll come back alive.
Okay. So if according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer she's only believed
for her co-wife once she acts on it, even when she acts
on it, we don't know she's acting on it. Maybe there's actually
a גט get that we don't know about. ולחוש שמא בגיטה אתאי,
veleichush shema begita asai,
she's coming with a גט. get. והאי דקאמרה הכי דבכולהו לצרתה היא
מכוונת. veha deka'amra hachi devichulhoi ltzarata hee mechavna. And therefore she's only
saying this to ruin her co-wife and that really her acting on
it doesn't prove anything. So
the
גמרא Gemara says: אי דאינסבה לישראל הכי נמי. ee de'insva l'Yisroel hachi
nami.
You know what? You're right. So if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer needs
her to act on it, it would not be enough to be
married to go ahead and marry a ישראל. Yisroel. Because maybe she
actually has a hidden גט get and she's not really acting on
it. אבל הכא במאי עסקינן דאינסבה לכהן. aval hacha bemai askinan de'insva
l'Kohen.
We'd only be talking about it that she married a כהן. Kohen.
So therefore it can't be that there's a hidden גט get because
then when all of that comes to light then she'll also be
ruined because she'll be married to a כהן Kohen and she'll have
to get divorced from him etc. Okay. So again it's very strange
because even if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer needs it to be backed
up by her acting on it, it doesn't mean you have to
eliminate any tiny little possibility of doubt. You know it's but so
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara goes where it does. But the
bottom line is you have רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position that once
a woman's testimony is believed for herself, it's believed for the other
woman even though these are other women that normally testimony would not
be believed for. And the question the גמרא Gemara has in doesn't
know bottom line is is that is do you need her to
actually have acted on her own testimony before you believe it for
the other woman or not. Yeah let's start over there, yeah.
How come yesterday we were very much concerned about the majority most
likely things that have happened and here we have only far-fetched concerns?
Well you mean why before could we sort of like we're not
concerned with the minority?
You know it's a good point. Meaning there we like know the
facts or I don't know if we know the facts but we
have like you know it's like it's like
here it's what standard do we need before we accept testimony into
evidence? Particularly testimony that normally would not be accepted into evidence, right?
The whole thing is an exception. There we've accepted the testimony in
the evidence, what are we going to do about the about the
facts that we don't know about? So you're right, it is a
little funny like we're willing to actually do act on something that's
only a fifty-two percent likelihood, right? When it's facts that we have
no access to but when it's actually a testimony and there's a
tiny possibility she might be lying we're not we're not willing to
accept it but it's it's you're right, I mean structurally it's different,
right? In one case we... In that case we don't have access
to that information and we have to make a draw a conclusion
based on, you know, based on statistics and likelihood. Whereas here, before
we can even admit the testimony, we have to feel relatively confident
that it's trustworthy. So I guess that's the difference. Here it's about
trustworthiness as opposed to there it's like using percentages to assess the
facts. But yeah, it's an interesting comparison. Yeah, that's something that I
keep on missing.
She has a גט. get.
So what we're concerned she might, yeah.
Right. Okay. So the צרה tzara then marries the brother-in-law?
No, this would be a case let's say of no brother-in-law.
Okay, so this woman has a גט. get.
Or maybe a brother-in-law.
How is that a קלקול kilkul to the צרה tzara then if
it's a hidden גט?
get? No, no, these two women are married to this guy. She
says he's dead. She actually has a secret גט. get. She goes
ahead and marries someone else, but he's doing it only to make
sure that רחל Rachel now goes ahead and marries a guy, whoever
the guy is. Then the husband comes back and says, "Hey, I'm
still alive." So רחל Rachel has been committing adultery, תצא מזו ומזו,
teitzi mizu umizu, and she has all this negative consequence where she
is saying, "I know you're alive. I got your גט get and
I'm go ahead and I'm still married to this other guy," right?
How is she committing adultery?
Because she's claiming that her husband is dead, their joint husband is
dead, when he's not. So רחל Rachel goes and gets remarried, right?
But she's still married to רחל.
Rachel. She's only not a
husband, he only gave her a גט. get. Exactly. Okay. All right.
Yeah.
I'm fine with that.
I thought courts, in American law, courts are like fact-finders, you know?
So if they make a ruling, it's considered a fact. And other
people can rely, assuming there were like similar interests and things like
that, on that fact. But here, when they say you're allowed to
remarry, they're not establishing a fact. Otherwise it would apply
exactly.
But רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer might be saying otherwise. That might be
רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer point, especially if he doesn't need the woman
to act on it. Once he's accepted your testimony for yourself, we're
going to accept it for other people as well. That might exactly
be רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer point. But you're right.
I mean, you're right, it's not a
fact. That this works within this, I mean, you know, and we,
I would say we normally wouldn't say, I'm not going to base
it on the fact that this is an exception and a special
like דין din that we're believing her when we normally don't, because
even by normal cases of testimony, there's סוגיות sugyos in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
called פלגינן דיבורא. palginan dibura. We split your words. We believe what
you're saying vis-a-vis somebody else, but not vis-a-vis yourself, or you know,
in this way and not in that way. So it's not something
that's unique to this case. You're right. I mean,
it's almost like living within a legal reality, not a real, you
know, not like this within הלכה halacha for halachic purposes we're believing
this, but we're not sort of necessarily asserting that we know this
to be a real-world fact, in objective terms. Right. Look, you know,
I mean, it's a conversation you often have, like how much is
הלכה halacha about establishing like, you know, real-world truth or establishing legal
truth? The very fact that you go by things like רוב rov
and חזקה, chazaka, does that mean that you know actually what the
facts are or that that's the assumptions that you make for legal
purposes, you know?
Even making the assumption in one case.
Yeah, but not always. Like for example, the classic case in the
גמרא Gemara is that there's two roads, right, and one of them
has טומאה, tumah, has like a dead body buried on it, and
the other does not. And one כהן kohen goes down one road,
or you know, somebody who has to bring a קרבן פסח korban
pesach goes down one road, and somebody goes down the other. And
each person comes to you individually, and for each person you פסקן
pasken that they're טהור. tahor. Because each one like is a ספק
טומאה ברשות הרבים safek tumah b'reshus harabbim and they both wind up
bringing קרבן פסח. korban pesach. One of them is definitely טמא, tamei,
right? But each case comes to, you know, so there's like a
lot of that. And maybe it's frustrating, but it's an interesting like
world to live in. Yes.
In contemporary law you could see them in terms of sometimes you
have technicalities, right, where you know that the guy committed the murder,
but you let him off because whatever. Or there's issues with precedent
where sometimes a ruling will explicitly say that this is a one-time
specific to this circumstance.
But this is one, but this is one case. They're all involved
in one case.
Yeah,
but is that really true? Like, I mean, I don't know, is
it true if somebody had like a criminal proceeding and a certain
thing was accepted, and then someone else, one state over, had had
a civil proceeding, would they be able to say, "Well, it's already
been determined in that other court the following facts?"
It depends on the relationship of the, if it's exactly the same
situation. Aha.
Okay,
but not always, not always something that's established by one court as
a fact can be then as it right, taken by another. So
that's sort of what the גמרא Gemara is doing, although you're right,
like these are tightly related, but he is dead or not.
Right. Right, but one court established he was. That's not relevant for
our court, right? When we're dealing with your, with whether your husband
is dead and you can remarry, we establish he is. When we're
dealing with whether her brother-in-law is dead, that's a separate court case,
it's a separate decision, and that's not... acceptable testimony for that. Right?
So it doesn't always work in American court like that either. All
right, last, last question guys. We are not going to fall behind
on our with two days to go.
Shh.
Yes. Just separately, Rabbi Elazar
refuted Rabbi Tarfon's opinion about that question of her being stuck or
not. If you recall last week,
which one, remind me?
I'll have to look at the דף, daf, but they were defending
one aspect but in the bottom line they were both they were
all saying she was stuck, the co-wife I think.
Yeah, I'll have to look at it, but but he's not saying
categorically I'm not going to let a woman get stuck, he's just
saying in this case I think it works, you know. Which case
was with a co-wife? Yeah, yeah, I'd have to look at that
case. Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה. mishnah. Now
we finally get to, so there's been a lot of fun talking
about, right, who's believed for whom and these interesting cases about but
now we actually get to the content of the testimony itself. How
do you know that a certain guy is the guy you're claiming?
So here's a testimony by the wife or by anybody that a
certain person died, a man died.
Here's how they say they recognized him. אין מעידין אלא על פרצוף
פנים עם החוטם. ein me'idin ela al partzuf panim im hachotem. אף
על פי שיש סימנים בגופו. af al pi she'yesh simanim b'gufo. You
can only testify
if you actually saw the face, okay, and together with the nose.
So the face with the nose is assuming we're saying that you
recognized him and you saw his face and you saw the nose,
that's considered to be like clearly you've identified him.
If you chop off the nose, there's nothing you can do?
I don't know, maybe I think saying you saw a chopped off
nose would count. Even though, I mean if you noticed him, if
you knew him before with a chopped off nose. If you only
knew him before with a nose, I don't know. אף על פי
שיש סימנים בגופו ובכליו. af al pi she'yesh simanim b'gufo u'v'kelav. Even
though you said, no, no, no, like you know I didn't see
his face but I could tell by his body, his stance, how
tall he was, tattoo maybe, or it was his clothes, I could
see I noticed his clothes, that's not enough. Has to be his
face. אין מעידין אלא, ein me'idin ela, now that's in terms of
who it is. Now how do
you know he's dead? אין מעידין אלא עד שתצא נפשו. ein me'idin
ela ad she'teitzei nafsho. You can only testify when you actually see
him dead. ואפילו ראוהו מגויד, v'afilu ra'uhu meguyad, even if you saw
him, רש"י Rashi says the word מגויד meguyad means like wounded, you
know like with you know
like with sort of piercings and cuts.
Jastrow translated as cut arteries. Apparently that was a way, yeah as
the גיד, gid, apparently that was a way that some places did
executions, okay? So even if you saw him severely wounded, cut arteries,
או צלוב, o tzaluv, or crucified, או חיה אוכלת בו, o chayah
ochelet bo, or an animal, a wild animal consuming him,
אין מעידין, ein me'idin, none of those cases is it acceptable because
you haven't actually seen him dead. He was still alive even though
it looked like he was going to die any minute, he was
still alive. Okay, so that's not enough. Now another point is אין
מעידין אלא עד
ג' ימים. ein me'idin ela ad gimmel yamim. Back to the question
about identifying him, you can only testify within three days of the
death. If you saw the body after three days of death, then
it might look, you know, the appearance will change and you might
not be correctly identifying, bloating or whatever, and you might not correctly
be identifying the body.
But you see the face with the nose.
Presumably. Right. רבי יהודה בן בבא אומר לא כל האדם ולא כל
המקום ולא כל השעות שווין. Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava omer lo kol
ha'adam v'lo kol hamakom v'lo kol hasha'ot shavin. You can't say three
days, right? Not every person is the same, some people their bodies
change quicker than others after death, not every place is the same,
right? Because you know, different climate, different heat, it depends on the
times, so therefore you cannot make this rule after three days you
can't testify. Okay? But we have this interesting thing first about identifying
the face and how do you know what it is and then
how do you know he's dead. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. פדחת ולא פרצוף פנים. padachat v'lo
partzuf panim. פרצוף פנים ולא פדחת. partzuf panim v'lo padachat. אין מעידין,
ein me'idin, you can't testify. עד שיהיו שניהם עם החוטם. ad she'yihyu
shneihem im hachotem. You need forehead, face and nose, you need like
to really see the whole face head-on. אמר אביי ואיתימא רב כהנא
מאי קרא, Amar Abaye v'itima Rav Kahana mai kra, what's the פסוק?
pasuk? הכרת
פניהם ענתה בם. hakarat pneihem antah bam. Recognizing their face
answered against them, that's like, you know, you were able to identify
them. And somehow רש"י Rashi says that that says means you need
the face rather than another part of the body. Yeah, the forehead.
תוספות Tosafot says somehow that the fact that it didn't just say
פניהם ענתה בם pneihem antah bam but הכרת פניהם ענתה בם hakarat
pneihem antah bam says that it has to be not just this
face but like a full identification of the face. אבא בר מרתא
דהוא אבא בר מניומי הוי מסיק ביה דבי ריש גלותא זוזי. Abba
bar Marta d'hu Abba bar Minyumi havah masik bei d'vei Reish Galuta
zuzei. So this אבא בר מרתא Abba bar Marta owed the ריש
גלותא Reish Galuta money, זוזי. zuzei. Is Abba bar Marta the same
person as
Abba bar Minyumi? Yes, he's the same person as Abba bar Minyumi,
that was his alias, okay. Anyway, and he owed the ריש גלותא
Reish Galuta money, זוזי. zuzei. אייתי קירא דבק באופלייתא, Aiti kira devak
b'avlayta, he took some wax,
he put it on like on a cloth... דבק באפוסיה Devak be'afusei
and sort of smeared it on his forehead. חלף קמייהו Chalaf kamaihu
and he walked in front of them, he had to get through
an area where they were,
ולא בסקרוהי Velo baskruha and they didn't identify him. They could—they didn't
recognize him. So he did a little bit, a little wax on
the nose, wax on the forehead, so he was able
to camouflage his identity. So it shows you how much like even
small
changes might mean that you're not—that you will be able to affect
whether you can recognize a person or not.
The guards weren't paying attention. Okay. Now, I want to say something.
So this obviously could make it very hard to testify that somebody
is dead. You have to see the whole face straight on.
Within three days essentially.
Yes, right. But, which we'll see about, but look at this תוספות
Tosfos just to see how like creative רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam was.
תוספות Tosfos says like this, top תוספות Tosfos of the דף. daf.
אין מעידין אלא על פרצוף פנים ואין מעידין אלא עד ג' ימים.
Ein me'idin ela al partzuf panim ve'ein me'idin ela ad gimmel yamim.
פירש משום דמשם ואילך משתנה. Peirush mishum demisham ve'eilach mishtaneh. Fine, after
that the appearances change. ואומר רבינו תם Ve'omer Rabbeinu Tam היינו דוקא
כשאין שם אלא הפרצוף. Hainu davka keshein sham ela hapartzuf. That this
is all you saw was the face.
Meaning, all you saw was the face.
אבל כל גופו שלם Aval kol gufo shalem if you saw the
entire body, אפילו אין כאן פדחת וחוטם Afilu ein kan padachas vechotom
ניכר הוא היטב על ידי סימני הגוף. Nikar hu heiteiv al yedei
simanei haguf. Even if you didn't see the forehead and the nose,
he's still identifiable based on identifying characteristics on the body. ועוד דשמא
דוקא בסימנים הוא דקאמר הכא אבל על ידי טביעת עין ניכר היטב
על ידי סימני הגוף. Ve'od deshama davka besimanim hu deka'amar hacha aval
al yedei tevi'as ayin nikar heiteiv al yedei simanei haguf. And even
though the משנה Mishnah says that you don't do it based on
marks on the body, maybe that's only when it's like a mark,
like, oh yes, there's a mole and I see a mole. But
there's a difference between I recognize him as opposed to—I can't exactly
point to, yes, I recognize him because he was six foot three
and this and that, no, I recognized him, like it's the whole
totality, it's an idea of recognition, identifying, and that maybe is fine.
And maybe when it says in the משנה Mishnah you can't go
by the marks, that's if all you have is the marks but
you don't actually recognize him.
Meaning you recognize him, can be even without a head, though תוספות
Tosfos says?
Yeah. Well, it's not totally clear whether you're seeing—maybe תוספות Tosfos is
saying you don't need the forehead and the nose, you need to
see some part of the face, but what's clear is he's trying,
ועוד דשמא דוקא סימנים אבל על ידי טביעת עין ניכר היטב על
ידי סימני גוף. Ve'od deshama davka simanim aval al yedei tevi'as ayin
nikar heiteiv al yedei simanei guf. כיון שיש כל גופו, Keivan sheyeish
kol gufo, since the body is complete. ואפילו אחר כמה ימים, Va'afilu
achar kama yamim, even after many days. Okay, and then he goes
on and on and he says like
this—one minute—okay, one
minute—and then like if we skip a little bit he says, ודבר
ידוע הוא שהוא ניכר אפילו אחר כמה ימים אפילו הוא אמת Vedavar
yadua hu shehu nikar afilu achar kama yamim afilu hu emes etc.
etc. And then like the last line just says like this—ותשובת רבינו
תם כתובה בספר הישר. Seshuvos Rabbeinu Tam kesuvah beSefer HaYashar.
The last line. Like, you know, so he wrote a whole—the רבינו
תם's Rabbeinu Tam collection of the רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam תשובות Teshuvos
is a ספר Sefer called ספר הישר, Sefer HaYashar, a collection of
חידושים chiddushim is also called ספר הישר. Sefer HaYashar. But the point
is—shh, yes—the point is is that תוספות Tosfos is obviously dealing with
a reality that this גמרא Gemara makes very hard, high thresholds of
being able to identify somebody, it's going to really make it hard
to marry off his wife. So what he does is that he,
you know, he re-reads some of these cases. So first of all,
the משנה Mishnah makes it sound like you need to see the
whole face and it says specifically that you don't do it based
on the סימנים simanim on the גוף, guf, and תוספות Tosfos basically
says well, you know, first of all, that's only if you don't
recognize him, then you have all these criteria, but if you can
say you recognized him even if you, you know, even by looking
at the body or whatever that's fine. And even if you don't
recognize him, even if it's just by certain like identifying marks, you
know, maybe if you have the combination of the body plus part
of the face even without all the criteria of the face, you
know, trying to really like re-read the גמרא Gemara to become a
much more flexible and contextual type of a standard, which is clearly
what was needed at the time, you know, or else they would
be really stuck.
So certainly fingerprints would be okay then.
Well, yeah, certainly that's true. But again, you really see the creativity
of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam by like changing what these things are
in the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara says only the face, not the
face with the body, it's talking only about identifying marks, not talking
about recognizing, and all those things would make a difference. Okay, let's
get back to the גמרא. Gemara. אף על פי שיש סימנים, Af
al pi sheyeish simanim, even though there are סימנים simanim on the
body, you do not—it's not sufficient. And again, you know, תוספות Tosfos
just told us סימנים simanim might mean identifying marks but it's not
the same as recognizing. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
למימרא דסימנים לאו דאורייתא. Lemeimra desimanim lav de'oraisa. That tells us that
identifying marks is not sufficient biblically, because it says identifying marks on
the body is not sufficient. ורמינהי, Uremineihu, I'll ask you on this.
מצאו קשור בכיס ובארנקי ובטבעת. Matzo kashur bekis uve'arnaki uvetaba'as. You found
a גט Get that was lost, and it was tied up to
a pouch or wallet or a ring. או שנמצאו בין כליו, O
shenimtzu bein keilav, or if it was amongst your other vessels.
אפילו לזמן מרובה, Afilu lizman merubeh, even if it had been a
long time since it had been lost, כשר, kasher, it's still a
valid גט. Get. So the question here is not just דיני ממונות
dinei mamonos concerned, like if I found, you know, your wallet and
it had your ID in it or something. It's a question about
can I trust that this is the גט Get that I wrote
for my wife and use it to divorce my wife with or
is it somebody else's גט? Get? So I had written a גט
Get for my wife... wife, but and then a גט get was
found. Just was found with the same names, I couldn't assume it
was mine because maybe somebody else has my name and has my
wife's name. But it was also found tied up to my wallet.
Okay? So then, okay, then I can assume it's mine. All right?
Even though I don't recognize the גט, get, you know, how what
I didn't pay much attention, the סופר sofer wrote it. I don't
recognize it. But it was tied to my wallet, that's enough and
that'll let me divorce my wife and it'll be, you know, acceptable
even for like weighty issues of אשת איש. eishes ish. Okay? So
you see that סימנים simanim work. אמר אביי לא
קשיא הא רבי אלעזר בן מהבאי והא רבנן. amar Abaye lo kashya
ha Rabi Elazar ben Mahavai ve'ha Rabbanan. It's a debate between רבי
אלעזר בן מהבאי Rabi Elazar ben Mahavai and the רבנן Rabbanan whether
you accept סימנים simanim for דאורייתא d'Oraisa purposes. דתניא, detanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, braisa, אין מעידין על השומה. ein me'idin al hashuma.
You cannot testify that you recognized a man in order to let
his wife remarry based on like a mole. רבי אלעזר בן מהבאי
אומר מעידין. Rabi Elazar ben Mahavai omer me'idin. You can, and presumably
this is also a mark on the body, not on the face,
not on the face at all. So מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai
lav be'ha kamiflegi, this seems like this is the debate: דמר סבר
סימנים דאורייתא, demar savar simanim d'Oraisa, you can use a סימן siman
for דאורייתא d'Oraisa purposes and therefore even a mark on the body,
right? That would certainly help רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam if we would
פסקן pasken that way. ומר סבר סימנים דרבנן, umar savar simanim d'rabbanan,
and some say it's only rabbinic, so that's why you need to
actually see the face, not just some mark on the body. אמר
רבא דכולי עלמא סימנים דאורייתא. amar Rava dechuli alma simanim d'Oraisa. Everybody
could hold that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא d'Oraisa and a mark on
the body, even on the body would suffice and that explains the
גט get case. So why does it not, so what's the debate
therefore about this about the שומה? shuma? והכא בשומה מצויה בבן גילו
קמיפלגי. vehacha beshuma metzuya beven gilo kamiflegi.
The question is, just because identifying mark works, what's the threshold for
an identifying mark? Right? Do people of the same בן גילו, ben
gilo, that's sort of the גמרא'ס Gemara's idea that people sort of,
I don't know, born in the
same מזל mazal or something like that, doesn't literally just mean the
same age, but in the same under the same astral influences, you
know, would have certain things similar to you. Okay? So the question
is, are these types of moles, will there be other people, will
there be other people like that are that, you know, that might
have them? מר סבר שומה מצויה בבן גילו ומר סבר אינה מצויה
בבן גילו. mar savar shuma metzuya beven gilo umar savar eina metzuya
beven gilo. Some say it will, some say it won't. So even
if everybody agrees that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, but you have
to get to the threshold where it's called a סימן, siman, where
it's called an identifying mark. Okay? So that doesn't explain though why
it doesn't work in the משנה. mishna. Now we're explaining that everybody
else holds that it's דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, the case of a גט, get,
the case of the שומה, shuma, we haven't yet explained why it
would not work in the משנה. mishna. Let's take, let's keep on
going. ואיכא דאמרי הכא בשומה העשויה להשתנות לאחר מיתה קמיפלגי. ve'ika d'amri
hacha beshuma ha'asuya lehishtanos le'achar misa kamiflegi. The debate is whether certain
things change after death, whether this mole will change after death. מר
סבר עשויה להשתנות לאחר מיתה ומר סבר אינה עשויה להשתנות לאחר מיתה.
mar savar asuya lehishtanos le'achar misa umar savar eina asuya lehishtanos le'achar
misa. One holds it will change, one holds it won't. So presumably
without the גמרא Gemara saying it, this is presumably where saying that
in the משנה, mishna, if you don't accept marks on the body,
that's because you're of the position that doesn't accept this שומה, shuma,
and either holds that they are not, that the marks on the
body are not identifying enough, or that they might change after death.
ואיכא דאמרי אמר רבא דכולי עלמא סימנים דרבנן. ve'ika d'amri amar Rava
dechuli alma simanim d'rabbanan. Some say, Rava said, everybody agrees סימנים simanim
only work for rabbinic purposes. Okay, so why does it work for
the גט? get? And why does it work for the שומה? shuma?
והכא בשומה סימן מובהק קמיפלגי. vehacha beshuma siman muvhak kamiflegi.
The question is, is a mole a סימן מובהק, siman muvhak, an
excellent סימן? siman? You know, meaning it's more than just a normal
identifying mark. It's like a fingerprint. It's a, you know, it's a
totally unique mark. מר סבר סימן מובהק ומר סבר לאו סימן מובהק.
mar savar siman muvhak umar savar lav siman muvhak. So of course
now you understand that like you've got a whole range of things.
Right? You've got things that nobody would say is a סימן. siman.
You've got things that everybody would agree is a סימן, siman, סימן
מובהק. siman muvhak. You've got things that are not identifying. And then
we've got this middle category that are somewhat identifying and that's where
we debate. So by the ways though, you're understanding why going back
to the רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, why you've got a certain amount
of latitude, because now we're introducing the possibility that even marks on
the body, some things we can identify as סימן מובהק, siman muvhak,
like your signature and right, and everybody would agree with them, right?
Some things we could identify, and then even if it's a middle
category of a standard סימן siman where we're saying that there's opinion
out there that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. Right? So we've now
opened up a wide range of possibility of accepting identifying marks on
the body. Okay? So let's take a look. ולאידך לישנא דאמר רבא
סימנים דאורייתא, ule'idach lishna d'amar Rava simanim d'Oraisa, according to the other
version that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, now we've got a problem.
What do you do and the whole issue was with the שומה,
shuma, right, whether that changes or doesn't change or whether other people
have it? So הא קתני אף על פי שיש סימנים בגופו ובכליו,
ha katani af al pi she'yesh simanim begufo u'vechelav,
that even though he has סימנים simanim on his body and on
the on his clothes, it's not enough. So what's that about? So
you could have said maybe it's the one that says, you know,
that the things change after death, but the גמרא Gemara understands that
that debate was only specifically about moles, about שומה. shuma. You know,
so but in general, in principle, everybody agrees that סימנים simanim are
דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. So then so why can't you use it in the
משנה? mishna? So the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, those wasn't even סימנים
simanim when it said in the משנה. mishna. גופו, gufo, when it
says סימנים simanim of the body, דאריך וגוץ. d'arich vegutz. Yeah, he
was tall, he was
short.
It's possible that everybody holds סימנים דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh, that's the case
by the גט, get, that's the case by what do you call
it, by the שומא, shuma, and maybe there's a debate specifically about
a שומא, shuma, but in general סימנים simanim is דאורייתא, d'oraiseh, and
certainly סימן מובהק siman muvhak is דאורייתא, d'oraiseh, okay, and the case
in the משנה Mishnah maybe even falls below the threshold of a
סימן siman altogether.
Do we have a פסוק pasuk in order to classify this as
דאורייתא? d'oraiseh?
Well, the גמרא Gemara actually in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia does have
a פסוק pasuk about השבת אבידה, hashavas aveida, okay, and that's where
a lot of the discussion about סימנים, simanim, no, because
it says שמלה simlah על
כל דבר פשע.
al
kol devar pesha.
No, no, not על כל דבר פשע. al kol devar pesha. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara has a פסוק pasuk in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
about returning אבידות aveidos which ties into this question of סימנים דאורייתא.
simanim d'oraiseh. Right, but even if you didn't have a דרשה, drasha,
you know, you could say דאורייתא d'oraiseh just as a question about
what do we assume the תורה Torah would determine demand as a
standard for identifying, right, what constitutes to be able to identify something
like, but the גמרא Gemara does tie it into a פסוק, pasuk,
you know, but all
these משניות mishnas were attached to אשת איש. eishess ish.
Well we have, yeah, but all these cases so far have been
אשת איש eishess ish cases. Now right, because the case of the
גט get is also אשת איש. eishess ish. So the גמרא Gemara
says like
this, what we basically have the following possibilities: either סימנים דאורייתא simanim
d'oraiseh and there was a specific debate by the שומא, shuma, but
in principle סימנים דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh, which would actually be a radical
leniency in our משנה, Mishnah, which you could remarry a woman based
on a mark on the man's body. And the only case in
the משנה Mishnah would be a case that didn't even qualify as
סימנים, simanim, okay. The other possibility that סימנים לאו דאורייתא simanim lav
d'oraiseh and a שומא shuma is special wouldn't explain the גט get
case. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara said if סימנים
דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh, the משנה Mishnah is a case where it's not
too identifying. The body is either tall or short, כליו דחיישינן לשאלה,
keilav d'chashinan l'sheila, and the clothes doesn't mean anything because maybe he
lent them. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, אי חיישינן לשאלה, ei
chashinan l'sheila, if we're afraid that people lend their things and that
will, you know, we can't therefore go by סימנים, simanim, so חמור
בסימני אוכף היכי מהדרינן? chamor b'simanei ukaf heichi mahadrinan? How would we
return a donkey if you can identify the saddle, which we know
you do in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, if you're afraid that people
lend things? Now, of course, as was pointed out, and תוספות Tosafot
raises, and I'm not going to sort of get into the answer,
but maybe we have different standards for remarrying a woman and for
returning a donkey, right, exactly. So anyway, okay fine, so shocking actually,
right. All right. So, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, where
were we? So the גמרא Gemara says היכי מהדרינן? heichi mahadrinan? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, לא שיילי אינשי אוכפא, lo sheili inshi
uchfa,
people don't lend out the saddle, דמסכא
ליה לחמרא, d'maska lei l'chamra, because it irritates the donkey's back if
you, you know, it if you have a saddle he's not used
to.
Otherwise it would be the same standard.
Yeah, exactly. מצא קשור בכיס בארנקי ובטבעת היכי מהדרינן? matza kashur b'kis
b'arnaki u'v'taba'as heichi mahadrinan?
How do you return the גט? get? It's not enough now to
say סימנים דאורייתא. simanim d'oraiseh. How do you return the גט get
if it's tied up to the pouch or to the wallet? Maybe
he lent his pouch and wallet to somebody else. So, right, the
גמרא Gemara says טבעת חיישינן לזיופא. taba'as chashinan l'ziyufa. No,
you don't give out your signet ring because you're afraid that somebody
will use it to forge. כיס וארנקי, kis v'arnaki, you don't lend
out your pouch and your wallet. מנחשי אינשי ולא מושלי. menachshi inshi
v'lo moshli.
People will do witchcraft on it because it's something a highly personal
object, so you know, so therefore you won't lend it out either.
It's sort of like יהודה Yehuda giving his staff and signet ring.
Anyway, but in general סימנים דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh, but it's just counterbalanced
by the fact that we're concerned that people lend things out. ואיבעית
אימא, v'iba'is eima, if you want I could say כליו דחוורי וסומקי.
keilav d'chivri v'sumki. We're not concerned that people lend things out. So
it's a much easier answer about the donkey and about the wallet
and whatever. So why then, if we're not concerned that you lend
things, can we not go by the clothes that the guy was
wearing? Because it says again, it's a case what was very generic.
Oh yeah, it was look like his clothes. I knew he was
wearing a white jacket, and I saw the guy with a white
jacket. So that type of generic doesn't believe. So what the גמרא
Gemara has now done is it basically said סימנים דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh,
which is why we return the גט. get. The case by the
שומא shuma is maybe a special case whether it changes after death,
but סימנים דאורייתא. simanim d'oraiseh. And you could identify on a man
that he's dead based on some type of identifying marks on the
body. You don't need the face. Your normal type of an identifying...
it can't be total, it can't be generic,
but a normal identifying mark would be fine. סימנים דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh,
right? A very big leniency from what we have in the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so now רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam חידוש chiddush is not
as radical. It says now, as long as you פסקן pasken סימנים
דאורייתא, simanim d'oraiseh, right? You've got the big category. And even if
you're by סימנים דרבנן, simanim derabbanan, there's still categories called... סימן מובהק,
siman muvhak, right, a really good identifying mark which would everybody would
agree on. Okay, now we get to knowing that he's dead. אפילו
ראוהו מגוייד, afilu ra'uhu meguyad, even if you saw him, you know,
wounded, cut, according to again maybe even with the artery severed, so
the- that's not enough. You can't say that he's dead, maybe he
survived. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא דמגוייד חיה, lemeymra demeguyad chaya,
are you telling me that somebody with an artery severed can actually
live? רמינהו, raminhu, I'll ask you on this. אדם אינו מטמא עד
שתצא נפשו, adam eyno mitamei ad shetetzey nafsho, we've got a משנה
Mishna that says a person does not cause טומאה tumah of corpse
until he has literally expired. אפילו מגוייד ואפילו גוסס, afilu meguyad ve'afilu
goses, even if he has the artery severed, even if he is
a גוסס goses which is like in the death rattle, the- you
know, the moments right before, I mean that's not really literally death
rattle. גוסס goses is but somebody that's literally on his like last,
you know, few deathbed, his last few death throes, well even that
I think a little bit too narrow. But okay, anyway, he's not
dead until he's dead. Of course the question is when is he
dead, which gets
into all the halakhic questions of defining death, right, the heart, the
lungs, the brain. Anyway, but whatever, the גמרא Gemara assumes you know
when he's dead. But when he's- even if you see that he's
dying and you think he's going to die in two minutes, he-
you know, it doesn't count as dead until he's dead for טומאה.
tumah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, טמויי לא מטמא, tumuyey
lo mitamei, fine, all it's saying is he's not yet dead to
cause טומאה, tumah, but המחיא לא חיי, hamachya lo chaya, the implication
is is that even though you know he's definitely going to die,
he's not dead yet. Oh my gosh, this just opens up the
whole Monty Python opportunity which I'm not going to do. "I'm not
dead yet". Okay, anyway, but okay, but even though he's not dead
yet, it's certainly clear he's going to die. So you assume מגוייד
meguyad will definitely die. אמר אביי לא קשיא, amar abaye lo kashya,
הא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר הא רבנן, ha rabi shimon ben elazar
ha rabanan, it's a debate of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon
ben Elazar and the רבנן Rabbanan whether you can assume that somebody
who's מגוייד meguyad will definitely die. דתניא, detanya, it's taught in the
ברייתא, Baraita, מעידים על המגוייד, me'idim al hameguyad, you can testify about
somebody with his artery severed that he's
dead, and not somebody that has been crucified.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, rabi shimon ben elazar omer, רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon ben Elazar says, אף על המגוייד אין מעידים,
af al hameguyad ein me'idim, even somebody that's artery severed you can't,
מפני שיכול לכבוץ ולחיות, mipnei sheyakhol lachvot velichyot,
because they can like shrivel and live, meaning somehow you can maybe
stop the
bleeding, cauterize them.
So that's what it is. So fine, our משנה Mishna assumes that
it's possible that he'll live, and there's another opinion, the רבנן, Rabbanan,
that assumes that he'll definitely die. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, והא אמרת דתוקמה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר, veha amita detukma k'rabi
shimon ben elazar, how could you say our משנה's Mishna רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon ben Elazar that says it's possible that he'll
live, והקתני סיפא, v'hatani seyfa, at the end of our משנה, Mishna,
which is really the משנה Mishna we're going to read tomorrow, says
the following: מעשה באסיא, ma'aseh b'asya, there was a story in Asia,
באחד ששילשלוהו לים, b'echad sheshilshulu leyam, somebody they lowered into the ocean,
maybe
doing some deep sea diving or something, ולא עלתה בידם אלא רגלו,
velo alta beyadam ela raglo, and when they raised him back up,
they pulled back up on the rope, all that was left apparently
the sharks attacked was his leg. ואמרו חכמים, v'amru chachamim, now the
point is is that it might be his leg was bitten off
but you don't know that he was consumed, maybe he managed to
escape and swim somewhere. All you know for sure is that his
leg was bitten off. ואמרו חכמים, v'amru chachamim, and the חכמים Chachamim
say, מן הארכובה ולמעלה תינשא, min harkuva ulemala tinasey, if it is
from the above the knee, so if somebody has his leg bitten
off from above the knee, he'll definitely die, even if all that
happened was his leg was cut off, but if was above the
knee he'll definitely
die, lose too much blood or something. מן הארכובה ולמטה לא תינשא,
min harkuva ulemata lo tinasey, below the knee, you cannot marry off
his wife. So what do you see? You see that this is
a case of essentially מגוייד, meguyad, okay,
where you know his arteries were cut because it was severed above
the knee, cutting some arteries, and nevertheless it is basically saying that
you can assume that he is dead. Okay, interestingly why below the
knee is not considered מגוייד, meguyad, but for whatever reason above the
knee is considered מגוייד. meguyad. So the גמרא Gemara says, תוספות Tosafot
point out you could have just asked the רישא reisha to the
סיפא. seyfa. The רישא reisha of our משנה Mishna assumes מגוייד meguyad
you can't marry off his wife. The סיפא seyfa assumes that if
his leg is cut off above the knee you can marry off
the wife. What's the difference? Both cases he's got some severed arteries,
why in the רישא reisha can you not and in the סיפא
seyfa you can? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, שאני מים דמירזז
מכה, shani mayim demirzaz maka, water is different because water irritates the
wound, okay, so therefore rubbing salt in the wound. So therefore in
the סיפא seyfa you can marry off his wife but in the
רישא reisha you can't. Okay, but we're assuming the רישא reisha is
generally the position of
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon ben Elazar that says that a
normal case of severed arteries you can't assume he's dead. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara ends by saying like this, והאמר רבה בר
בר חנה, veha'amar raba bar bar chana, didn't רבה בר בר חנה
Raba bar bar Chana say, לדידי חזי לי ההוא טייעא, ledidi chazi
li hahu taya, I saw a certain like Arab nomad, דשקל ספסירא,
deshakal sapsira, he took his sword, וגיידיה לגמלא, vegaydey legamla,
and he severed (מגוייד, meguyad, see the word מגוייד meguyad there), he
severed the like a leg of his camel. something of his camel,
ולא אפסיקתיה לנעורתיה velo afsiktiah line'urasei
and it didn't not stop its moaning. Now, what exactly that means
is not clear. רש"י Rashi makes it sound like it means that
he, that the camel moaned and then expired on the spot. And
then the question would be that you see that מגוייד meguyad an
animal that is something that's מגוייד meguyad will die. And how could
you be saying that according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar it won't die? But of course that's not a good
point because we're not saying it never dies, we're just saying it
might not necessarily die. So the alternative reading which is going to
work as the second answer is that somehow means that the animal
continued to live even though he severed.
לנער Lena'er means to shake.
Oh, but רש"י Rashi says it means, רש"י Rashi says if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, ולא אפסקיה לנעורתיה, velo afsikei line'urasei, לנעורתיה, line'urasei,
לא הפסיק לגמור את כל נערותו lo hifsik ligmor et kol naaruto
שהיה נוער. shehaya no'er. נוער No'er
means to moan, right? עד שמת. ad shemet.
Maybe it's a verb for moaning for camels. You know every animal
has its own verb.
All right, anyways, maybe. So anyway, apparently although it sounds from the
way I read רש"י Rashi that it means that the camel died
immediately, that really doesn't work because the fact that sometimes something dies
as a result isn't a proof. The proof is if it lives,
right? And that's going to be clear from the end. So presumably
he chopped off the leg of his camel and the camel lived.
Okay, so you see that this somehow proves maybe it proves like
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. So how could there
be חכמים Chachamim that say that you can assume the guy died?
You see that this case happened and it lived. The גמרא Gemara
says אמר אביי Amar Abaye הכי כחישה הויא. haki kachisha havya. That
was thin. I don't know it's a thin camel. So a thin
womb? Sickly? No, but again the assumption here is it lived. So
somehow the fact that it's thin means that I don't know somehow
it's going to have the same effect. רבא Rava said בסכין מלובנת
דברי הכל. besakin meluvenet divrei hakol. I know it's a little funny
because until now it sounds like he died and we're trying to
explain why he died. But the second answer is רבא Rava said
בסכין מלובנת דברי הכל. besakin meluvenet divrei hakol. It is a was
a white-hot knife and therefore it cauterized and therefore everybody would agree
in that case it can live because that case it cauterizes the
wound. That's what רש"י Rashi says. So presumably the evidence was that
the animal lived. How can you say that how can the רבנן
Rabbanan say it's possible he dies? We have clear evidence that he
lives. And says no, that was a special case. Okay, but we
basically have the debate of רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar whether רבנן Rabbanan will say he will רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says it's possible he'll live
and the רבנן Rabbanan will say definitely die and according to the
רבנן Rabbanan they would be even easier also to testify. So notice
we're constantly introducing more broader you know application in the משנה. Mishnah.
The משנה Mishnah says identifying marks on the body is not enough.
We've identified a whole class of identifying marks on the body which
are totally fine, right? Certainly סימן מובהק siman muvhak and even a
סימן siman that's not מובהק muvhak if you say סימנים דאורייתא. simanim
de'oraita. The משנה Mishnah says if you see somebody with severed arteries
you can't assume he's dead and we've introduced the position of the
חכמים Chachamim against רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that
says you can assume that he's dead. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
continues. הייתה חיה אוכלת Hayta chaya ochelet and an animal was eating
his body also you can't assume he's dead. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel לא שנו אלא ממקום שאין נפשו
יוצאת. lo shanu ela mimmakom she'ein nafsho yotzet. That's only if the
animal is eating like a leg, a place where
the soul well
right but okay a place where the soul doesn't leave. במקום שנפשו
יוצאת Bemakom shenafsho yotzet but let's say an animal's chewing at his
neck or something like that in that case מעידין me'idin you can't
testify. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Va'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel שחט
בו שנים או רוב שנים וברח מעידין. shachat bo shenayim o rov
shenayim uvarach me'idin. But didn't רב יהודה Rav Yehuda say in the
name of שמואל Shmuel that if somebody has you know shechted two
of the סימנים simanim meaning the trachea and the esophagus or the
majority and he ran away that you can testify?
Right early on
he's not necessarily going to die from a place where the
right no ואימא ve'eima it's not ואמר va'amar ואימא רב יהודה אמר
שמואל שחט בו שנים או רוב שנים וברח מעידין. ve'eima Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel shachat bo shenayim o rov shenayim uvarach me'idin. So that's
consistent meaning the same way if the animal is chewing away at
the neck you can testify or away at the head or something
like that the heart you can testify. Similarly רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says in the name of שמואל Shmuel that if somebody had the
trachea and the esophagus cut or the majority of them cut you
could also assume he died. So even if cut arteries is somewhat
debatable right a cut throat is not debatable.
Okay, so it's not even mentioned in גיטין Gittin that he שחט
בו שנים או רוב שנים shachat bo shenayim o rov shenayim and
he said give me a גט.
get. Oh that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay,
but let's take a look. איני Eini is that true? ואמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל שחט בו שנים או רוב שנים ורמז ואמר כתבו
גט לאשתי הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel shachat
bo shenayim o rov shenayim veramaz ve'amar kitvu get le'ishti harei elu
yichtevu veyitnu that if somebody has the trachea and esophagus cut and
he signals to say write a get for his wife you can
go ahead and do it. Now the reason he's doing this sounds
funny but why would he do it? Why would he want his
wife divorced the minute before he dies?
So she no she won't marry her יבם. yavam. יבום. Yibum.
יבום. Yibum. No no she gets a כתובה ketubah anyway.
Guys what מסכת masechet are we learning? Get out of the brother-in-law
get out of יבום. yibum. Okay, so in that case you can
do it. So how can you say that with a cut trachea
and esophagus he's definitely going to die? The גמרא Gemara says what's
the problem? The גמרא Gemara says חי הוא וסופו למות. chai hu
vesofo lamut. Right now he's alive so you can go ahead and
write a גט. get. I don't know how long it will take
you and how long you can assume he will still live but
right. But right, but you can go ahead and write a גט.
get. He is. The point is, and by the way, this is
very important in terms of the halachic definition of death, that even
with somebody who has a severed trachea and esophagus, halachically they're alive.
Okay, even though, so they're still, they will be alive, I mean,
whatever for a few more minutes, right? But it's interesting because people
want to say that brain death is sort of like a severed
head or anyway. The point is, yes, so I mean I don't
know how long,
but halachically dead suggested though for an animal.
Fine, yes, that's true because animal doesn't have a גט, get, it
just has to be שחטed. shecht Okay, so anyway, so we have,
so he is halachically alive. The point of the משנה Mishna in
גטין Gittin is not that he won't die. Of course he's going
to die. The point is halachically he's alive. And if you can
write a גט get and give it to his wife before he
dies, it's a good גט. get. So the גמרא Gemara says, what's
the problem? He's alive, but he's going to die very soon. So
you can testify for his wife that she can remarry. חי הוא
וסופו למות. chai hu v'sofo lamut. אלא מעתה ela me'ata says the
גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, יגולה על ידו, yigole al yado, if
a person does this to somebody accidentally, they should be sent into
exile, right, accidental death, if it means that it'll definitely die as
a result. אלמה תניא, alama tanya, why do we teach in a
ברייתא, braita, שחט שנים או רוב שנים, shachat shnayim o rov shnayim,
if somebody accidentally cut the trachea and esophagus of another person, הרי
זה אינו גולה, harei ze eino goleh, he don't go into exile?
Why is that? If you'll say that this wound will definitely cause
death, why should it not be the basis of גלות? golus? So
the גמרא Gemara says, הא איתמר עלה, ha itmar alah, it was
said on it, אמר רב הושעיה, amar Rav Hoshaya, חיישינן שמא הרוח
בלבלתו, chayshinan shema haruach bilbelato, we're afraid that other
factors might have contributed to the guy's death, like after because he's
got this wound, the wind came and whatever and it irritated it
and it speeded up the death. I'll talk about it in a
minute. אי נמי שמא הוא קירב מיתתו, inami shema hu kirev mitato,
maybe he himself speeded up his own death. What would be the
case? The case like he started getting, he shook and he got
nervous and all of that speeded it up. מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu,
what's the difference? דשחטיה בביתא דשישא, deshachte beveisa deshisha,
let's say you שחטed shecht him, the guy got שחטed shecht in
a house of marble, which was completely protected from any outside influences
and the wind, ופרכס, uperches, but he himself shook, so he might
have speeded up his own death but it wasn't because of the
wind of it. אי נמי דשחטיה בברא ולא פרכס, inami deshachte bevara
velo parches, or he שחטed shecht him outside so there was wind
but he didn't rattle and shake and therefore there's a concern of
the wind and not a concern of his own thing, of his
own thing. Now, of course this is a little bit absurd because
for God's sake, the guy did it, he definitely died as a
result, who cares if there were other contributing factors or not? I
by the way should point out that there was, I don't know
if you saw this story, front page New York Times about a
week ago, about a guy that was wounded 35 years ago and
he just died and based on
the autopsy, they realized that his death 35 years later was as
a result of the wounds he had received and now they're trying
to prosecute a case 35 years backwards for murder.
97 years
old, but because of a wound he received 35 years ago that
brought about his death 35 years later they want to prosecute
the guy for murder. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafot points out that if
it was an intentional wounding and somebody was שוחט שנים או רוב
שנים, shocheit shnayim o rov shnayim, then of course we wouldn't care
if there were other things that contributed. That wound, that's like that
case in the New York Times, that wound was the thing that
brought about the death, it would have killed him anyway whether other
things speeded it up or not is irrelevant. But for a case
of גלות, golus, we have a lot of exceptions, if people ever
learn מכות. Makkot. Are you going up? Are you going down? Exactly
this degree of שוגג, shogeig, not that degree of שוגג. shogeig. So
there's a lot of exceptions for exile and there we say it
has to 100% be from this guy and not and if there's
anything else that was a factor that gets you off. So תוספות
Tosafot says this is particularly an issue about גלות, golus, not an
issue about, we would not be the same standard at all if
it was intentional murder, then of course the person would be חייב.
chayav. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says so when you're שוחט שנים
shocheit shnayim it'll definitely bring about the death, but there might be
other contributing factors and if there are other contributing factors there would
not be גלות. golus. Okay, so we'll end with this. What?
The heart's going to stop potentially?
Yeah, I guess so.
And
the other question is what I found interesting is רבי יהודה בן...
Rabbi Yehuda ben...